A Guide to the Williams Family Papers, 1819-1993
Thomas Balch Library
Gordon Williams returned to the United States in 1919 after serving with the Army of Occupation, and took a job as a stock broker at Wade, Templeton & Co. He left the brokerage house in October of 1923 when United Sugar Company hired him as Resident Vice-President of its holdings in Los Mochis, Sinaloa, Mexico. He died there of fever on 4 October 1925. His body was returned to the United States and buried next to his parents in Buffalo.
While his father was posted in England from 1886-1890, Harrison Williams attended University School in Nottingham, and from 1890-1891 he attended Chateau de Lancy School near Geneva, Switzerland. Following the family's return to Buffalo in 1891, Harrison Williams read law at Sprague, Morey, Sprague & Brownell, one of the city's leading law firms. Williams joined the 65th Regiment of Infantry of the New York National Guard and served from 1891-1892. He attended law school at University of Buffalo, graduating in 1893, and was admitted to the bar the following year. Williams practiced law until 1897, when he accepted a job as tax agent for the Erie Railroad Company in New York City. He retained ties to Buffalo, although he resided most of his time in New York City. In 1902 he became head of the tax department, and in 1907 was named head of the General Land and Tax Department of the Erie Railroad System, specializing in tax law.
On 8 May 1901, he married Jane Kirby Abbott (4 March 1875-22 May 1909) in Marshalltown, Iowa. She was the daughter of Albert Cutler (10 October 1836-7 January 1903) and Mary Watson (15 August 1840-?) Abbott. In 1890 Abbott and his family moved from Marshalltown to Chicago where Jane attended Dearborn Seminary, graduating in June 1894. In September 1894 Abbott was made vice-president of National Linseed Oil Company and moved his family to Buffalo. He and his wife moved back to Marshalltown after he suffered paralysis in1897.
Harrison and Jane Williams had one child, Harrison Jr., born in New York City on 6 February 1904. By 1907 Jane had become seriously ill and moved back to Marshalltown to stay with her mother. It was hoped that retiring to the country would help her recover, but she died in 1909. Harrison Jr. stayed with Jane's sister and brother-in-law, Albert G. (1861-?) and Helen A. (1864-?) Glick in Marshalltown while his father worked in New York City.
Harrison Williams married a second time in 1910. He and Pauline Marechal Winslow (1 July 1872-29 November 1933) wed December 29, and departed soon after on a six month trip to Europe. Pauline, daughter of William Grandy (14 April 1845-17 September 1910) and Ida Stone (14 May 1847-16 June 1896) Winslow, was born and educated in Buffalo. She later studied art in Dresden for several years. Pauline was a descendent of Kenelm Winslow (1599-1672), one of the early settlers of the Plymouth Colony in Massachusetts. Her husband's brother-in-law, Frederick Bradlee Winslow, was also a descendent of Kenelm Winslow, making them distant cousins.
Harrison and Pauline Williams' son Winslow was born in New York City on 10 February 1913. When Williams retired from practicing law later that year, the family moved to Williamsted, a farm Williams had purchased several years before located outside of Leesburg, Virginia. He had built a large residence on the property which he used as a vacation home. Williams sold the farm in 1920, and in 1923 he bought another piece of Loudoun County property on which he built a house he called Roxbury Hall, named for an ancestral home in Massachusetts.
Harrison Jr. joined his family at Williamsted in 1913. He was enrolled in Episcopal High School near Alexandra, Virginia in 1918, graduating in 1922. He entered University of Virginia (UVA), where he earned a Bachelor of Science degree in engineering in 1928. While at UVA, he was active in a number of clubs and organizations. After graduating he took a job as a junior engineer in the Virginia State Highway Department. On 22 July 1928 Williams was thrown from the back of a motorcycle he was riding with a friend on a trip from Danville, Virginia to visit friends in North Carolina. He was taken to a hospital in Danville where he died of his injuries the same day. His father described his death as a crushing blow to family and friends.
Harrison Williams Sr. was widowed a second time in 1933 when Pauline died at Roxbury Hall on November 29 after a long illness. Williams continued to live in Loudoun County, as did their son Winslow. Williams enjoyed traveling, and made a number of trips abroad.
Harrison Williams met Joan Stafford-Allen (1907-2003) during a transatlantic voyage from England in 1937. She was the daughter of Mr. and Mrs. George Stafford-Allen (n.d.) of Long Melford, Suffolk, England. The two became friends during the journey, and Williams invited her to visit Roxbury Hall when they arrived in the US. After she returned to England they continued to correspond. He surprised her with a visit to her home, where he proposed, in 1938. They were married on 17 August 1938 in the National Cathedral in Washington, DC. After they returned from a two-week wedding trip the couple settled in the new home Williams built on West Market St. in Leesburg next to Thomas Balch Library. The Williams both were involved with Thomas Balch Library, and Harrison Williams served as president of the library from 1925 until his death.
Williams had a life-long interest in writing. He wrote poetry as a child, and in his retirement pursued historical research and writing. He undertook a project to write a book about important individuals and places in Loudoun County's history, Legends of Loudoun: An Account of the History and Homes of a Border County of Virginia's Northern Neck, published in 1938. He also wrote articles about local history. During World War II, Harrison was asked to serve as Loudoun chairman for Virginia's War History Committee in 1943. The committee was organized by Virginia Conservation Commission's Division of History and Archeology in 1942 and used local correspondents to collect newspaper clippings and reports about war efforts from localities around the state. The Commission produced Virginia in War Time, 1942-1943, a sketch of people's activities and attitudes.
An avid genealogist, Williams spent many years researching his family history. In October of 1932 he received a letter from Samuel Asbury (1872-1962), an amateur historian in Texas who was researching the life of Jonas Harrison. Williams was astonished to learn of Harrison's life after he disappeared from Buffalo in 1819. He and Asbury subsequently corresponded regularly to update one another on their research. Williams published his work, The Life, Ancestors and Descendants of Robert Williams of Roxbury: In His Majesty's Province of Massachusetts Bay in New England, 1607-1693, which traces the family back to its earliest American forebears in Massachusetts in 1934. He was able to assist Asbury with information he needed for the article on which he was working, "Jonas Harrison, Legendary and Historical," published in Southwestern Historical Quarterly in 1942.
After her husband's death in 1946, Joan Williams went back to her family home in Suffolk to care for her mother. She returned to Leesburg when her mother died, and worked at Loudoun Hospital caring for premature babies. She was also active in other community activities, continuing her interest in Thomas Balch Library and in Oatlands Plantation, where she served as a docent for 24 years. Joan Williams died 27 September 2003.
Winslow Williams attended school in Leesburg until 1929 when he was enrolled in Episcopal High School, where he stayed until 1931. He also attended Shenandoah Valley Academy, a preparatory school for boys in Winchester, Virginia. After graduating, he lived at Roxbury Hall with his father.
Williams married Helen Constance Moore (3 September 1918-10 September 1991) on 6 February 1937. They had three children, Winslow Jr., Harrison III, and Constance. A keen outdoorsman, Williams was a strong supporter of the Boys Scouts and served as a scoutmaster in the 1950s. He enjoyed bird watching, and frequently took his camera with him when he was outdoors.
He operated a real estate business, Winslow Williams Real Estate, in Leesburg and was one of the founding members of Loudoun County Board of Realtors. Helen Williams also worked in the real estate business. Williams was an avid photographer, and took pictures both for pleasure and for the Loudoun Times Mirror. For a time Williams operated a photography studio in Leesburg; he closed it in the 1950s. In 1991he donated his collection of nearly 10,000 negatives to Thomas Balch Library. Helen Williams died 10 September 1991 after a long illness. Winslow Williams died on 19 February 1993.
Winslow Family (Series V)
Richard Winslow was born in Falmouth, Maine 6 September 1769. Little information is available about his life prior to his arrival in Ocracoke, North Carolina in 1812, where he engaged in land and marine commerce. He married Mary Nash Grandy (June 1788-18 October 1858) of Camden, North Carolina. They had eleven children: Nathan Crane (10 December 1812-9 June 1880), Richard Grandy (23 September 1814-20 May 1854), Hezekiah Jones (8 December 1815-31 December 1883), Rufus King (15 September 1817- 7 October 1892), Henry Knox (31 March 1819-30 September 1826), Cyrus Homer (12 December 1820-2 September 1824), Lydia Jane (28 July 1822-13 September 1824), Edwin Newton (26 February 1824-?), Caroline Susan (7 April 1826-8 April 1832), Harriet Williams (28 March 1828-13 April 1832), and Mary Jane (30 January 1831-13 April 1832).
The family moved to Cleveland, Ohio in 1830. Winslow predicted there would be business possibilities in Cleveland with the completion of the Ohio and Erie Canal, and he bought a piece of property on the river for a warehouse. Later in 1830 he traveled to the east coast and purchased groceries and other goods which he sent back to Cleveland with Nathan to open a store. Winslow had a considerable amount of capital which he invested to develop his shipping interests. He built his business into a sizeable enterprise, becoming one of the largest operators on the Great Lakes with a fleet numbering around 40 vessels.
In 1832, Richard Winslow purchased a lot on Euclid Avenue at the southeast corner of the public square and contracted master builder and architect Levi Johnson (1786-1871) to build a house. Many of Cleveland's wealthiest families lived on Euclid Avenue, and by the middle of the 19th century the street was lined with mansions on expansive lawns. The family lived there until Richard Winslow's death in 1857, when the house was torn down.
Three of Richard Winslow's sons married three sisters, the daughters of Dr. Welcome Arnold (25 April 1792-?) and Mary (ca. 1800-?) Clarke. Hezekiah Winslow married Helen Clarke (2 September 1825-?) in 1846. They lived in New York City and Cleveland, and had two children, Richard (26 September 1848-11 April 1896) and Helen Brighty (26 September 1850-15 December 1867). Richard Winslow married Mary Aphia (?-July 1933); they lived in Buffalo, New York and Paris, France. Little information is available about them.
Rufus K. Winslow joined the family business around 1852. After his brothers Nathan and Hezekiah left Cleveland, Rufus Winslow controlled the Cleveland operations. He married Lucy Clarke (12 June 1820-?) in 1852. In addition to his business interests, Winslow also spent time engaged in scientific research and became a well regarded amateur ornithologist. The couple had one daughter, Annie Clark Winslow (?-19 April 1926). Annie married John Chadwick (n.d.) and spent most of her life in Paris, France.
Nathan Winslow married Mary Anne Clarke (1 October 1815-10 March 1885) in 1839, and joined his father's shipping business. The Winslows had four children, Caroline (23 September 1839-?), Henry (23 December 1840-14 Dec ember 1876), George (January-July 1843), and William G. (14 April 1845-17 September 1910). Nathan Winslow relocated to Buffalo in 1862, where he established a business with his son Henry and son-in-law John Williams (25 December 1837-?). After her husband's death in 1880, Mary Anne Winslow spent most of her time travelling in Europe. She died at her daughter's home in Baltimore, Maryland in 1885.
William G. Winslow married Mary Ida Stone (14 May 1847-16 January 1896) in 1868. They had six children - Mary S. (n.d.), Helen Brightie (1870-?), Pauline Marechal (who married Harrison Williams), Marie Louise (1875-?), Henry Clarke (1877-?), and William Gaston (24 September 1882-?). The family lived in Buffalo, and also spent a number of years abroad. Marie married Frederick B. Ussher (1 September 1863-?) in 1901; they lived in Buffalo.
Scope and Content
The Williams Family Papers includes materials from five families: Pearce, Wilson, Harrison, Williams, and Winslow. The papers comprise approximately six cubic feet, with five oversized boxes housing documents and artifacts. Inclusive dates are 1819-1993, with the bulk of the material dating from 1850-1945. The collection is arranged in series by family name, with the papers of individual family members as subseries. While in most cases the papers are in very good condition, for preservation purposes photocopying is not permitted.
Series I: Pearce Family, 1819-1859
Subseries I: George Pearce, 1819-1822
George Pearce's papers consist of correspondence from his wife, Eliza. They show the difficulties the couple faced being separated for long periods of time while he was deployed.
Subseries II: Eliza Pearce, 1819-1859
Eliza Pearce's correspondence is largely from family and friends including George Pearce, her mother-in-law, Rebecca Pearce (n.d.), and Jane and Mary Wilson. Her husband wrote about his concerns for her well-being and that of their daughter while he was at sea. In the years after her husband's death, letters illustrate her difficulties in obtaining pension payments. Of interest are three autographed letters signed (ALS) from Benjamin Watkins Leigh on 28 March 1829, 5 July 1833, and 24 March 1834 regarding Eliza Pearce's pension claim. Copies of congressional bills in the collection regarding the Navy Pension Fund demonstrate the process of extending payments to widows. Eliza Pearce's papers also include receipts and bills related to housekeeping.
Series II: Wilson Family, 1831, 1848
The Wilson Family materials consist of three letters. Two are to Jane Wilson, and there is also a letter to Jane from her mother, Mary Wilson.
Series III: Harrison Family, 1842-1911
Subseries I: Betsey Cooke Harrison, 1872, n.d.
There are three items related to Betsey Cooke Harrison: a lock of hair, her obituary, and an undated carte de visite.
Subseries II: James C. Harrison, 1842-1882
James C. Harrison's papers include correspondence from his wife and daughter, including letters from Mary while she was at school and from both on their trip abroad after Mary finished her studies. Other letters relate to business and his efforts on behalf of Eliza Pearce. Papers from Harrison's estate include obituaries, letters testamentary, and a resolution by Erie County Savings Bank board of directors recognizing his death.
Subseries III: Mary Wilson Pearce Harrison, 1833-1911
Mary Wilson Pearce Harrison's papers include letters from her mother, Eliza Pearce, while she was at school, and letters from Mary and Jane Wilson. Later correspondence includes letters from her husband James Harrison and daughter Mary. Of interest are letters from 1863-1864 written by Mary while she was in school in New York City which discuss unrest during the Civil War, particularly the attempt to burn the city in 1864. Other materials include receipts and a prescription from 1870. Mary Wilson Pearce Harrison's estate papers include correspondence, copies of wills and other legal documents, and receipts.
Series IV: Williams Family, 1862-1993
Subseries I: William Williams, 1862-1876
William Williams' papers contain correspondence; business records such as checks, legal agreements, bills, and stock certificates; and miscellaneous items such as brochures from Walnut Hill School, certificate from his election to Congress, and the Civil War Commission for his son Griffin Stedman Williams from 1862. Of interest in Williams' correspondence are an ALS from Samuel J. Tilden from 13 May 1867 regarding a business agreement; ALS from Schuyler Colfax about an offer of a railroad ticket dated 10 April 1871; and an ALS from William W. Belknap to A.M. Clapp, 5 June 1872 with a denial of request for clemency.
Subseries II: Lovisa Stedman Williams, n.d.
There is one item for Lovisa Stedman Williams, an undated letter.
Subseries III: Griffin Stedman Williams, 1853-1911
Griffin Stedman Williams' papers contain correspondence, with the bulk from his friend Horatio Seymour, mostly during the 1860's, and son Harrison Williams. Other correspondents include his mother, father, and brother. Also of interest are two ALS from sculptor Hiram Powers (1805-1873) regarding Williams' purchase of a marble bust of Proserpine. Other materials include Williams' Civil War orders, with one document signed by Brigadier General F.B. Spinola; cards of introduction and other mementos from his trips abroad; and a handwritten bet with Joseph Ely on the 1860 presidential election. Later records include receipts for Williams' care as his health declined and papers from his estate.
Subseries IV: Griffin Stedman and Mary Harrison Williams, 1871-1895
There is a small number of letters to Griffin Stedman and Mary Harrison Williams from Harrison Williams, mostly written while he was at school at Chateau de Lancey in Geneva. There is also correspondence about both estates, which were handled by Harrison Williams as executor, regarding insurance, storage of belongings, and bills.
Subseries V: Mary Harrison Williams, 1864-1910
Mary Harrison Williams' correspondence includes letters from her father and mother while she was at school in New York City with news about family, friends, social happenings, and the family's pets. There are additional letters from her schoolmates, as well as from her husband-to-be Griffin Stedman Williams. Other items in her papers include bank books, cancelled checks, and a stamp collection. Mary Harrison Williams' estate papers include a copy of her will, inventories, and bills and receipts.
Subseries VI: Gordon Williams, 1896-1922
Gordon Williams' papers consist of four letters, which include an invitation to his brother Harrison's wedding and a letter from the Department of the Navy with information about the service record of George Pearce.
Subseries VII: Harrison Williams, 1882-1946
Harrison Williams' papers include a large number of letters received throughout his life. Early correspondence is largely from his parents, particularly his mother, while he attended school, and contains news from home. There are letters from his first wife, Jane (also called Jennie), and following her death from Harrison Jr. after he went to live with her sister and brother-in-law, Helen and A.D. Glick, in Marshalltown, Iowa from 1909-1913. Helen Glick also wrote to Harrison Williams Sr. with news about his son. During World War I, Williams' brother Gordon wrote describing his attempts to enlist and finally his deployment to Europe. A large portion of the letters concern Williams' genealogy research. From 1932 until his death in 1946 he exchanged frequent letters with Samuel Asbury regarding Jonas Harrison. There are also some handwritten copies of Williams' outgoing letters.
The papers contain research notes from several writing projects, including Legends of Loudoun and The Life, Ancestors and Descendents of Robert Williams of Roxbury, 1607-1693. The papers also contain typed and manuscript drafts of Legends of Loudoun. There are notes and reports from Williams' service as Loudoun chairman for Virginia's War History Committee in 1943. A copy of the Committee's publication, Virginia in War Time, 1942-1943, is also in the collection. Other items include receipts, cancelled checks, club memberships, an oath of attorney from 1904, and World War II memorabilia. Included in the artifacts is a book of poetry written by Williams as a boy.
Subseries VIII: Harrison and Jane Williams, 1901, 1904
There is a small amount of material for Harrison and Jane Williams: a set of place cards made by Jane in watercolor and pencil for their wedding breakfast, and correspondence about the birth of their son, Harrison Jr.
Subseries IX: Jane Abbott Williams, 1903-1904, n.d.
Jane Abbott Williams' papers contain a small number of letters from family and friends in 1904, mostly cards and letters of congratulations on the birth of Harrison Jr. There is also one letter from Harrison in 1903. Jane is often referred to as Jenny or Jen.
Subseries X: Harrison and Pauline Williams, 1910-1920
Harrison and Pauline Williams' papers include correspondence. Letters from 1917-1920 are mostly from Harrison's brother Gordon about his efforts to get in the army and his experiences during the World War I. A small number of German postcards from February 1919 are included. There are also letters to the Williams from Helen Glick about Harrison Jr. while he was living with her and her husband in Marshalltown; some include letters from Harrison Jr. as enclosures. Much of the correspondence from 1929-1930 is from Winslow while he was away at school.
Subseries XI: Pauline Marechal Winslow Williams, 1910-1935
Pauline Marechal Winslow Williams' papers consist of correspondence, financial records, and memorabilia. There are letters from friends and family, brother Gaston. The bulk of the correspondence dates between 1929 and 1930, with a large number of letters from Winslow while he was at school with news of school, plans for visits, and requests for various items. The papers include a number of items related to Pauline's financial affairs, such as bank books, stock purchases, cancelled checks and receipts. Other items such as lists of wedding gifts, a confirmation card, and gift tag from Winslow's first Christmas are also in the collection.
Pauline Winslow Williams' estate was complicated due in large part to her interests as a legatee in real estate in Buffalo and Cleveland. The papers include a number of legal documents and correspondence regarding the Euclid Avenue property (often referred to as the Cleveland property) originally owned by Richard Winslow. His heirs retained ownership of the Euclid Avenue property on which the family house had stood. In 1907 May Company signed a 50-year lease at $32,000 per year with the heirs, to commence in 1909. The company built its flagship Cleveland store on the site. By the early twentieth century, ownership of the property had become increasingly complex. As one generation of heirs died additional legatees were created, making a complicated system of fractionalized interests in the property. In addition, some of the heirs sold their interests to Nathan L. Dauby (31 May 1873-17 May 1964), vice-president of May Company.
Dauby filed a partition lawsuit in 1934 to force sale of the property and divide the proceeds among the owners. He argued that ownership had become so complicated it was no longer an attractive investment for him. Harrison Williams, representing the interests of his wife Pauline's estate and their son Winslow, contended that Dauby sought to buy the property at a depreciated price. At a meeting in June of 1934, legal representatives for the heirs decided to allow the partition suit to proceed, and sale of the property to May Company went forward in 1935.